<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
  <!ENTITY spacer '&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;'>
  <!ENTITY homepath '.' >
  <!ENTITY shorttalk_ad SYSTEM "ads/ShortTalk.xml" >
  <!ENTITY foot_ad SYSTEM "ads/footad.xml" >
  <!ENTITY mouse_ad SYSTEM "ads/mousead.xml" >
]>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>Nils Klarlund CTD (RSI) musing</title>
    <meta name="author" content="Nils Klarlund"/>
    <meta name="copyright" content="Nils Klarlund, 2003"/>
    <meta name="description" content="Nils Klarlund CTD (RSI) musings"/>
    <meta name="keywords" content="Nils Klarlund, RSI, CTD, repetitive
    stress injury, cumulative trauma disorder, personal experience,
    tendinopathy, tendinitis"/>

    <link rel="stylesheet" href="klarlund-netscape4.css" type="text/css"/> 
    <style type="text/css"> 
      @import url(klarlund.css);  <!-- non-netscape 4-->
    </style>

    <ads>
        &shorttalk_ad;
	&foot_ad;
	&mouse_ad;
    </ads>


  </head>

  <body column_format="one">

    <tabs>

      <tab name="CTD-RSI" title="Cumulative Trauma Disorder (a.k.a. RSI)"
	   column_format="two" horizontal_contents="yes"  ads="no">
	<related>
	  <item href="http://bmj.com/cgi/content/full/324/7338/626"
		title="Tendinitis: were you misdiagnosed?  (external)" > CTD or
	    RSI is often diagnosed and treated as tendinitis.  This
	    editorial in the British Medical Journal states that
	    overuse injuries are not tendinitis and are not associated
	    with inflammation.  Moreover, the <a
						 href="http://bmj.com/cgi/eletters/324/7338/626#20629">
	      tendinopathy</a> paradigm advocates strength training, not
	    rest as the primary treatment.
	  </item>
	  <item href="http://www.tendinosis.org" title="Chronic
		tendon injuries (external)">The web site <a
							    href="http://www.tendinosis.org">tendinosis.org</a> gives an
	    excellent overview of the social and medical aspects of tendon
	    injuries, a very common manifestation of CTD.
	  </item>
	  <item href="http://www.engr.unl.edu/ee/eeshop/rsi.html" title="Computer
		Related Repetitive Strain Injury (external)">Paul Marxhausen's site
	    contains a very good collection of advice and useful
	    links.
	  </item>
	  <item href="http://www.mousewatch.com" title="Mousewatch.com
		(external)">
	    This site is well-organized and up-to-date.
	  </item>
	  <item href="http://www.ctdrn.org/" title="CTD Resource
		Network (external)"> This organization provides information and
	    assistance in the area CTD.  It maintains the <a
							     href="http://www.tifaq.org">Typing Injury FAQ</a>
	    site.
	  </item>
	  <item
		href="http://xenia.media.mit.edu/~cahn/rsi/meditations"
		title="RSI reflections (external)" >Humorously and
	    seriously, Janet Cahn explains what she
	    learned at MIT about RSI.
	  </item>
	</related>
	<em>Cumulative Trauma Disorder</em> (<em>CTD</em>) and
	<em>Repetitive Stress Injury</em> (<em>RSI</em>) cover an
	array of poorly understood soft tissue problems.

	<a name="Personalstory"><h3>Personal story</h3></a> I am
	recovering from a such a problem, a typing injury sustained in
	December of 1992 (tendinitis in forearms).  In the beginning,
	I went through multiple cortisone injections, heat and cold
	treatments, massage, physiotherapy, muscle release therapy,
	arm braces, casts, and long periods with minimum typing.  For
	several years, I let my wife drive; I pushed typing work onto
	my co-authors or secretaries; and I experimented relentlessly
	with alternative treatments and input devices.  The first four
	years, nothing helped---except not typing.  Then,
	DragonDictate, an early speech recognition program, together
	with foot switches, slowly allowed me to use my arms less.
	<p>
	  I have tried most kinds of ``ergonomic'' aids available:
	  dozens of pointing devices, several keyboards, and various
	  instruments for stabilizing upper extremities.  I have
	  concluded that most are ineffective and that some are
	  harmful.  Initial positive impressions almost always turned
	  out to be wrong.  There is some commercially available
	  equipment that I prefer, see <a
					  href="input_devices/index_setup.html">my setup</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
	  Additionally, I have vigorously pursued ideas of my own.  I
	  have constructed three kinds of keyboards, several foot
	  switch arrangements, and a dozen mouse designs.  They have
	  generally failed my own trials. The exceptions are the ideas
	  I put forward in <a href="input_devices/index.html">Input devices,
	    a usage-driven approach</a>.  
	</p>
	<p>Speech recognition plays a very important role in my daily
	  work.  I have found dictation system user interfaces rather
	  unusable because of their slowness and incompleteness.  For
	  six years, I have researched alternatives.  Out of these
	  frustrating efforts has emerged an editing language I call
	  <a href="ShortTalk/index.html">ShortTalk</a>.  Measurements
	  indicate that ShortTalk combined with limited pointing on
	  the average may be much faster than conventional means of
	  editing.
	</p>
	<p>Lately, I can easily type for an hour or so, and finally my
	  arms are well enough that I can travel with a normal load of
	  luggage.  But half a day at the keyboard still produces
	  flare-ups lasting a couple of days.  With my workspace setup
	  explained in <a href="index_uisummary.html">User interface
	    summary</a>, I can work all day with no adverse affects.
	</p>
	<h3>Added August, 2002</h3> <p> In the spring of this year,
	  around the time I wrote the description above, I started
	  old-fashioned strength training with handweights.  I tried
	  that before but gave up because of pain.  When I started
	  again, my dominant arm (which had been hurting me the most)
	  was markedly weaker than the non-dominant one.  After
	  six-months of training, I am handling 30 lbs. weights (along
	  with smaller ones depending on the exercise), and pain
	  levels have subsided further.  Then, interestingly, I just
	  found out, see sidebar, that strength training according to
	  a new tendinopathy paradigm is the primary treatment, not
	  rest, heat, massage, or stretching.  However, I wonder
	  whether not the drastic reduction of the offensive ways of
	  working that led to the injury should still be a primary
	  intervention as well.  Also, I find it difficult to gauge
	  how much pain should be endured during exercise; sometimes,
	  I find myself hurting for several days after, but in the
	  end, the effect seems to be positive.  

	    <h3>Added September, 2003.</h3> <p>This will be the last
	      update because there has been slow but tremendous
	      progress over the last year.  I'm still using both foot
	      keyboard and speech recognition to distribute the load
	      of working on computers.</p>
	</p>
      </tab>
    </tabs>
  </body>
</html>

