<html>
  <head>
    <title>Nils Klarlund -- ReX, towards a foundation for multimodal,
    multimedia applications</title>
    <meta name='author' content='Nils Klarlund'/>
    <meta name="keywords" content="multimedia, SMIL, IVR-system,
    VoiceXML, multimodal, speech recognition, error correction"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="klarlund.css"/>
  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>ReaX---towards a foundation for multimodal,
    multimedia applications</h1>


    <div class="abstract">
      <p>Solving a universal user interface problem, the ReaX
	programming language forces the buttons <div
	style="text-align: center; margin:2ex;" xmlns:DSD="yyy"
	xmlns:asr="zz" xmlns:ReaX="vvv" xmlns:v="vvv1"
	xmlns:SMIL="SMIL"><button>|&lt;</button><span>
	</span><button>&lt;&lt;</button><span>
	</span><button>&gt;&gt;</button><span>
	</span><button>&gt;|</button><span>
	</span><button>pause/play</button></div> to always work. (The
	button marked "|&lt;" is the undo function, the button marked
	"&lt;&lt;" is the rewind function, the button "&gt;&gt;" is
	the forward function, and the button "&gt;|" is the redo
	function.)  
      </p>
      <p>Modern user interfaces are often needlessly irking to use,
	simply because the prosaic problem of providing consistent and
	workable undo and seek mechanisms have been ignored by
	programmers.  Speech enabling applications not already
	designed with undo leads to offensive designs.  Moreover,
	small buttons on new devices and generally difficult-to-use
	applications make the lack of a general undo mechanism a basic
	problem that we show is readily solvable.  Our main
	technical contribution is a new technique for tying declarative
	reasoning about time and synchronicity  to the basic
	notion of event.
      </p>
    </div>

<p>The simpleness of HTML contributed to the explosive growth of the
Internet.  But what is the content format that will do the same for
multimedia content?  The format must combine temporal notions for
media coordination, such as SMIL (a W3C recommendation), and a
reactive programming language, such as Statecharts or a multithreaded
version of Ecmascript.</p>

<p>
However, a well-known and fundamental semantic conflict exist between
a declarative style of specifying temporal relationships and the
programming that addresses user and system events.  We propose a new
multi-threaded, XML-based scripting language---ReaX---that introduces
a notion of <em>reaction tree</em> for capturing causality among
events.  We show how the explicitly tree-oriented semantics of ReaX
overcome semantic problems in reactive languages and SMIL.
    </p>

	<p>Our initial work with <a
      href="http://www.cs.wisc.edu/~jbeckham/">Jennifer Beckham</a>
      and Giuseppe di Fabbrizio outlined how a SMIL-like notation,
      then called ReX, would form a basis for a reactive language with
      declarative, temporal features.  You can see our ideas in <a
      href="papers/Rex-Eurospeech01.pdf">our paper</a>.
    </p>

    <p>The document <img src="gifs/new.gif" alt="new"/>``<a href="papers/ReaX-language-draft.html">ReaX: an
      undoable, timed synchronization language</a>'' presents <ul>
	<li>a concrete design of a reactive core language,</li>
	<li> a
      concrete event semantics of ``synchronous'' broadcast, and
	</li>
	<li>an explanation of how undo and real time seek mechanisms
	are uniformly treated in the reactive core language
      </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
      <p>
      The <img src="gifs/new.gif" alt="new"/><a href="talks/ReaX.htm">survey talk</a> (html) [<a
							  href="talks/ReaX.ppt">Powerpoint</a>] explains my general
     interests in user interface technology and how they lead to
     fundamental questions about events and synchronicity.</p>
  </body>
</html>

