<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
  <!ENTITY spacer '&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;'>
  <!ENTITY homepath '..' >
  <!ENTITY shorttalk_ad SYSTEM "ads/ShortTalk.xml" >
]>

<!-- Ergonomic designs are critically examined. Use over design is -->
<!-- emphasized. Fundamental problems, such as mouse buttons, as well -->
<!-- as new ideas, such as foot pedals,  are discussed-->

<html>
  <head>
    <title>Input devices: a usage-driven approach</title>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8"/>
      <meta name="author" content="Nils Klarlund"/>
      <meta name="copyright" content="Nils Klarlund, 2002"/>
      <meta name="keywords" content="Nils Klarlund, input devices, RSI,
	    CTD, mouse design, keyboard design, foot keyboard, foot switches,
	    scroll wheel"/>
    
    

    <link rel="stylesheet" href="../klarlund-netscape4.css" type="text/css"/> 
    <style type="text/css"> 
      @import url(../klarlund.css);  <!-- non-Netscape 4-->
    </style>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="index.css"/>

    <related>
      <item href="../index_uisummary.html" title= "A Low-Impact Workspace">
	A description of how a low-impact workspace can be put
	together using speech recognition and techniques in this essay.
      </item>
      &shorttalk_ad;
      <item href="../index_ctd-rsi.html" title="Background">My
	motivation for researching user interfaces is a long-standing
	typing injury.
      </item>
    </related>

  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>Input devices: a usage-driven approach</h1>

    <tabs>
      <tab name="Introduction">
	<related>
<item href="http://www.tendinosis.org" title="Chronic
		       tendon injuries (external)">The web site <a
							href="http://www.tendinosis.org">tendinosis.org</a> gives an
	    excellent overview of the social and medical aspects of tendon
	    injuries.
	  </item>
	  
	</related>

	<quote>
	  Some of these accessories are valuable, but a lot of
	  them are gimmicky, if not downright dangerous.
	  <where>Pascarelli &amp; Quilter in <em>Repetitive stress
	      injury</em>
	  </where>
	</quote>
	<p>I am writing this essay to summarize my years of
	  experiments with input device design.  My interest is born
	  out of a long-lasting typing injury, but I have no formal
	  training in ergonomics.  I hope to provide a critical and
	  realistic view of what can be done to improve input devices.
	  The goal of course is to fundamentally reduce the strain on
	  hands and arms when using the computer.  It is actually
	  possible, I believe, to work in a fashion that is
	  dramatically easier on hands, arms, and shoulders.  There is
	  no miracle: it involves (1) speech recognition and mastery
	  of a system of voice commands (2) use of a reduced-impact
	  pointing device that may be shoved around by one or two
	  hands, and (3) a foot pedal arrangement.  
	</p>
	<p>
	  Neither of these techniques are commercially available; nor
	  have they been tested in long-term experiments by
	  others---the expensive and only way of establishing claims
	  of ergonomic superiority.  However, the proposals I present
	  have been subjected to my own daily usage for several years.
	  They represent but a fraction of ideas and commercial
	  products that I have attempted to use long-term.
	</p>
	  <p>The main point of this essay is that input device design
	  is very difficult, even though there are often simple
	  explanations why a design is potentially injurious.  I will
	  give several examples of input device designs that are
	  superficially appealing, but seemingly devoid of functional
	  qualities that make them usable in ways that fundamentally
	  reduce physical stress.  Rather, by their very
	  construction, some alternative designs hold the potential of
	  being more harmful then the traditional designs they are
	  intending to replace.
	</p>

	<p>The patent literature is brimming with input device ideas.
	  Engineers, doctors, and lay people have investigated mouse
	  surface curvatures, twistings of the keyboard, wearable
	  gizmos, etc.  These initiatives apparently have had little
	  impact in reducing pain and injury from computer use.</p>
	
	<p>Even the popular "ergonomic" split keyboards have not been
	  shown to have any health benefits; a proof, if possible,
	  would involve long-term studies involving thousands of
	  individuals.  The theory that these keyboards are easier on
	  body because they involve less ``deviation'' of the hands
	  relative to the forearm is plausible.  But maybe more
	  plausible is the opposite hypothesis: what matters is only
	  how you use the keyboard.  Moreover, the opposite hypothesis
	  argues that since the standard keyboard is smaller it better
	  allows your hands to manipulate the mouse and to find a
	  resting position.  So, it is already clear that the
	  so-called ``ergonomic'' keyboards are ``ergonomic'' in name
	  only; they represent another compromise among a host of
	  competing design constraints.</p> <p>This kind of analytical
	  thinking about various stresses on the body incurred by use
	  of devices is important to anybody who is struggling with
	  pain from computing, since it is one way of raising body
	  awareness.  This is especially true since the innumerable
	  negative experiences with ``ergonomic'' equipment go
	  unreported.  Whether it be a speech recognition program or
	  an especially ``ergonomic'' mouse design, the technology is
	  usually disappointing. The defeat is not broadcast to
	  colleagues and friends.
	</p>
	<p>Why do keyboards and mice hurt people?  Nobody seems to
	  really know.  At a cellular level, the processes behind CTD
	  remain a mystery, although it is believed that inflammation
	  is not a necessary component, see <a
	  href="http://www.tendinosis.org">tendinosis.org</a> for
	  pointers to medical literature.  At the functional level, it
	  remains unproven that repetitive motion is to blame.  For
	  example, another functional culprit could be the constant
	  stress the body is experiencing when near the devices.</p>
	  <p>To understand this, think about replacing each key on the
	  keyboard and each button on the mouse with a little hot
	  plate glowing red.  If you were working next to such a
	  monstrous instrument, then you would condition your limbs to
	  be constantly adjusting themselves so as not to touch any of
	  more than one hundred hot plates.  The point is, of course,
	  that even when keyboard and mouse do not posses thermal
	  properties, your body must be conditioned exactly the same
	  way.</p>

	<p>The mouse is particularly bad, since the hand tends to ride
	  it.  Consequently, fingers must be forced upwards to not
	  press the hot plates.<img align="right"
	  src="../gifs/hand-on-mouse.gif" alt="Arrow showing static
	  stress force when using mouse"/> Extensor muscles, the arms'
	  weakest ones, are continuously struggling to keep this
	  unnatural balance even if the brain thinks that the hand is
	  at rest.  Interestingly, preschool kids struggle quite a bit
	  with this likely injurious principle.  Whereas they may
	  easily learn to type out their own name on the keyboard, it
	  may take several more months for them to learn to hold the
	  mouse without pressing the buttons---an indication that the
	  mouse is anything but natural.</p>

	<p>In my judgement, there are three areas where new thinking
	  may lead to less pain when using a computer.  For the
	  keyboard, there is only little room for improvement---still
	  I have some modest ideas, see <a
	  href="index_keyboard.html">keyboard</a>.  In contrast,
	  the mouse may be an essentially harmful device that cannot
	  be improved within its traditional design constraints---see
	  my proposal in <a href="index_mouse.html">mouse</a> for a
	  different concept.  Finally, I suggest how foot pedals can
	  very effectively complement a keyboard or speech recognition
	  for repetitive tasks in <a href="index_footpedals.html">foot pedals</a>.</p>
	
	<p>My opinions and proposals are the result of a decade of
	  personal experimentation and observation.  That's why I call
	  this overview a "usage-driven approach".  The information I
	  offer here should not be construed as advice.  I do not know
	  whether my observations are generally applicable.  If you
	  have pain, then go see a doctor.  The only recommendation I
	  offer to others with typing or mouse injuries is to look in
	  the excellent book <em>Repetitive strain injury</em> by Emil
	  Pascarelli and Deborah Quilter (John Wiley and Sons, 1994).
	</p>
      </tab>
      <tab name="Mouse">
	<quote>
	  I doubt they were built for hand
	  safety: mice inherently strain the hand...
	  <where>
	    Pascarelli &amp; Quilter in <em>Repetitive stress injury</em>
	  </where>
	</quote>
	  <p>
	    The mouse is a spoiler.  Whenever you put your hand on it,
	    you stress your body.  If for a moment you forget to apply a
	    lifting force to your fingers, then buttons are immediately
	    activated.  Consequently, your body must work constantly with
	    shoulder, limb, hand, and finger positions to not press
	    buttons.  Unless, of course, you take your hand away from
	    the device.  Something the size and shape of it discourage
	    you from doing.  The lighter the mouse buttons are to
	    depress, and the bigger they are, the more static force is
	    needed to prevent accidental mouse clicks.  Thus, curiously,
	    there may be a direct relationship between how "ergonomic"
	    the mouse is and how harmful it is.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	    The keyboard is much more forgiving in this regard.  It is
	    natural to rest the hands in front of the keyboard as soon
	    as they are not in use.  But given that the mouse inherently
	    forces an unnatural, constant muscle response, I believe
	    that researching mouse curvatures alone is an exercise in
	    futility.
	  </p>
	  <h3>The buttonless mouse</h3>
	  <p>
	    Instead, mouse buttons must be entirely removed from the
	    pointing device itself.  This is not a radical idea: on
	    laptops, the pointing device (stick or pad) is separated
	    from the buttons.  Also, the new mouse feature called a
	    scroll-wheel should be moved to the keyboard.  The mouse is
	    the last place another function should be placed.  Finally,
	    the proper mouse size is less than the standard one.
	  </p>

	  <p>Now what are the consequences?  The series of pictures
	    below illustrate five of numerous ways a small, buttonless
	    mouse can be manipulated.  (The mouse shown has actually its
	    buttons disabled.)  Most of these poses are not possible with
	    a conventional mouse unless various fingers are
	    counter-balanced to not depress the buttons.
	    <table class="pictures">
	      <tr>
		<td><img src="../photos/Mouse-1hand-finger-ride.jpg"
			 alt="One-handed finger ride"/><br/>
		  One-handed finger ride
		</td>

		<td><img src="../photos/Mouse-1hand-side-grasp.jpg"
			 alt="One-handed side grasp"/><br/>
		  One-handed side grasp
		</td>

		<td><img src="../photos/Mouse-1hand-thumb-grasp.jpg"
			 alt="One-handed thumb ride"/><br/>
		  One-handed thumb ride
		</td>
	      </tr>
	    </table>
	    <table>
	      <tr>
		<td><img src="../photos/Mouse-2hand-shove.jpg"
			 alt="Two-handed shove"/><br/>
		  Two-handed shove
		</td>
		
		<td><img src="../photos/Mouse-2hands.jpg"
			 alt="Two-hands semi-ride"/><br/>
		  Two-hands semi-ride
		</td>
	      </tr>
	    </table>
	  </p>
	  <p>These pictures indicate how an appropriate shape allows the
	    the mouse to be manipulated by just putting a part of the hand
	    on top of it, while the side of the hand still rests on the
	    table.  This easy-on-off principle encourages the hand to rest
	    on the desk, not on top of the mouse.  It is still possible to
	    have the hand ride on top of the mouse---while the hand gets
	    gets a lot of support both from the desk, because the mouse
	    fits in the palm of the hand, and from the mouse itself,
	    because of the lack of buttons.  Note that to use the mouse in
	    such varied ways, where hands are given plenty of resting
	    areas, more space is needed than what is usually available on
	    a keyboard tray.  That's why I believe that reducing keyboard
	    size, or getting rid of it by combining speech recognition and
	    foot pedals, is very important.</p>

	  <h3>And where do the buttons
	    go?</h3>
	  <p>
	    The buttons may go on either side of the keyboard or be foot
	    activated.  In <a
			      href="index_keyboard.html">keyboard</a>, I propose
	    how scrolling functionality and mouse buttons can be
	    conveniently combined on a keyboard.  This arrangement will
	    not slow you down: as one hand is leaving the keyboard to
	    locate the mouse, the other slides to the side where the
	    buttons are easily found.  And, in <a
						  href="index_footpedals.html">foot pedals</a> I
	    consider available and future foot switches.
	  </p>
	  <h3>Trials</h3>
	  <p>
	    I believe that it would be interest to carry out controlled
	    trials of simplified, buttonless mouse designs.  If the
	    design of the mouse impacts its injury potential, then a
	    study is more likely to demonstrate this effect the larger
	    it is.  The removal of buttons may offer the best chance for
	    obtaining such an effect.
	  </p>
      </tab>

      <tab name="Keyboard">
	<quote>Pointers---self taught typists who hunt and peck
	  instead of touch-type---...are the least likely to be hurt
	  from their style.
	  
	  <where>Pascarelli &amp; Quilter  in <em>Repetitive
	      stress injury</em></where>
	</quote>


	<p>From bitter experience, I don't believe that the keyboard
	  can be improved much.  Three times, and without success, I
	  have built whole keyboards from scratch.  Nevertheless,
	  there are a few changes I would like to see done to the
	  keyboard:
	  <ul>
	    <li>A smaller footprint allowing more rest areas for hands
	      and a mousing area closer to the center of the body.</li>

	    <li>Widely spaced modifier keys so they can be pressed by
	      the side of your hand instead of requiring pinky
	      contortions.</li>

	    <li>Mouse buttons on the side so as to allow a buttonless
	      <a href="index_mouse.html">mouse</a>.
	    </li>

	    <li>A scroll tread or belt on the side of keyboard to make
	      browsing possible without dependence on finger-skills.  A
	      large scroll wheel might also be sufficient instead of the
	      more complicated thread mechanism.</li>

	    <li>A numeric keypad that does not make the keyboard as
	      wide as normal 101-key models.</li>
	    
	    <li>A flat design, akin to that of a laptop keyboard, but
	      with 3mm key travel and good mechanical feed-back.
	    </li>
	  </ul>
	</p>

	<h3>Why keyboards have gotten less ergonomic</h3> 
	<p>
	  For modifier keys, such as <tt>Ctrl</tt> and <tt>Shft</tt>,
	  ergonomicity has declined.  When they are widely spaced
	  apart <img align="right" width="100"
		     src="../photos/spacing-left-modifier.jpg" alt="Widely spaced
		     Ctrl and Alt keys"/> as on keyboards made in the mid '90s,
	  these keys can be depressed easily with the side of the hand
	  or with the outer side of the curled-up little finger, all
	  while the thumb is facing upwards<img width="100"
						src="../photos/good-modifier-use.jpg" alt="Pressing modifier
						keys without strained uses of fingers" align="left"/>.  In
	  this way, the strenuous finger work usually associated with
	  chording is avoided.  Unfortunately, modern keyboards suffer
	  from extraneous OS-specific keys that prevent this technique
	  from being used.  (Except if these keys are uprooted or
	  lowered.)  On a flat keyboard, such as on a notebook
	  computer, fingers are even further restrained by the
	  flatness from hitting keys in a variety of ways---something
	  that is likely an ergonomic drawback.
	</p>
	<h3>A keyboard layout proposal</h3> 
	<p>A keyboard  
	  layout following these ideas mentioned above is suggested in 
	  <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>.  Below it's shown (left) how a
	  large, comfortable belt may be placed on the left side of the
	  keyboard, along with mouse buttons; the side of the hand
	  (right), not the fingers, securely moves the belt.
	</p>
	<div class="picture">
	  <img src="../photos/scroll-keyboard1.jpg"/> 
	  <img src="../photos/scroll-keyboard2.jpg"/>
	</div>
	<p>These ideas and the figure below are from AT&amp;T
          Technical Disclosure <a href="../keyboard/keyboard.html">A keyboard design</a> by Nils Klarlund.
	  <hr/>
	  <a name='fig1' >
	    <div style='text-align: center; position: absolute; left: 0;' class='picture'>
	      <img src='../gifs/scroll-keyboard.gif' alt='Keyboard layout'/>
	      <br/>
	      <a href='../keyboard/keyboard.html'>Click for bigger picture</a>
	    </div>
	  </a>
	</p>
	<!-- create the vertical space -->
	<div style="height: 530px;">&spacer;</div>
      </tab>

      <tab name="Foot Pedals">
	<quote>One of the most popular misconceptions about
	  computer work is that it is an ``easy'' activity, when in
	  fact it is quite strenuous for your hands and arms.
	  <where>Pascarelli &amp; Quilter in 
	    <em>Repetitive
	      stress injury
	    </em></where>
	</quote>
	<p>Obviously, foot pedals cannot replace the keyboard.  But it is
	  intriguing that many of us use our strongest limbs to control
	  safety-critical pedals while going to or from work, while the
	  same limbs stay underemployed under the desk all day.  The
	  problem is that using just two a three pedals as in the car
	  will not cover enough of repetitive work to make a difference.
	  For example, even processing incoming e-mail requires at least
	  five keys (next message, previous message, scroll down, scroll
	  up, and delete message).  And, naturally, typing with our feet
	  must be considered a hopeless task for most of us.
	</p>
	<p>Speech recognition offers an excellent alternative to
	  typing, even as it seems hopeless at repetitive work.
	  Saying "page up", "page up", "page down" to browse through a
	  web page speaks for itself.  So, maybe the combination of
	  speech recognition and foot pedals is the combination that
	  will effectively offload the hands?
	</p>
	<p>This was my thinking when I started using speech
	  recognition six years ago.  Initially, I used five or six
	  foot switches glued to a wooden board.  Through several
	  iterations of pedals arrangements, I arrived at a basic layout
	  that can be seen in the photos below.
	</p>
	<div class="picture">
	  <img src="../photos/footkeyboard1.jpg"/> 
	  <img src="../photos/footkeyboard2.jpg"/>
	  <img src="../photos/footkeyboard3.jpg"/>
	</div>
	(For a technical disclosure, see <a
					    href="http://www.delphion.com/details?pn=US05889510__">US5889510
	  Foot-operated keyboard device</a>) 

	<p>In this design, each foot may operate seven front keys
	  placed around the sides and front of the foot.  Most common
	  keys are present: the arrow keys, enter, backspace, space, and
	  tab. In addition, left and right mouse buttons are present
	  (see <a href="index_mouse.html">mouse</a> why this is
	  important).  Also, there are an undo key and three keys
	  important to speech recognition: repeat last voice command,
	  correction, and microphone on/off.  All of these keys are
	  commonly used.  But 14 keys don't suffice.  So, other common
	  functions such as "page up", "skip over left word", "change
	  window focus", "go to the beginning of line" and "go to end of
	  document" are activated through a combination of a front key
	  and one of two modifier keys behind the foot.  The idea is to
	  step forward on a front key with one foot while the heel of
	  the other presses the modifier.  The modifier pedals are
	  two-level switches, so altogether the keyboard offers 14 * 5 =
	  70 foot-activated functions.  A <a
					     href="../video/footkeyboard.wmv">video</a> (streaming Windows
	  Media) (<a href="../video/footkeyboard.mpg">mpeg-1</a>
	  (28Mb)) of a version of this keyboard is available.
	</p>

	<p>The design shown here is crude; it is possible to devise
	  much better working key shapes.
	</p>

	<p>I have used this design for four years.  In my experience, the
	  combination of speech recognition, based on the editing
	  language <a href="ShortTalk.html">ShortTalk</a>, buttonless
	  mouse, and foot pedals is significantly more efficient than
	  the keyboard + mouse combination.  This efficiency is
	  important: it is <em>the</em> driving force for using the
	  combination.  It is extremely difficult not to work in one's
	  old ways if the new ways are not superior.
	</p>
      </tab>

      <tab name="Skeptical Remarks">
	
	<quote>The public should be skeptical about claims of
	  ergonomic superiority...
	  <where>
	  Pascarelli  &amp; Quilter in <em>Repetitive stress
	    injury</em></where>
	</quote>
	<p>Although some ``ergonomic'' accessories or devices may fit
	  certain people, I believe that there are easily argued reasons
	  why most of them may not work or may even be harmful.  These
	  opinions are examples only, offered to stimulate critical
	  thinking.</p>

	<h4>Forearm rests</h4> 

	These often elaborate mechanical contraptions support your
	forearm even while in motion over the keyboard.  But a
	fundamental misunderstanding may be a play here: the muscles
	of the forearm lift a heavy object, the hand, that is not
	supported by forearm rests.  So, the full weight of these
	long, bony structures still have to be born by the forearms.
	And, perversely, the forearm rests may make it cumbersome to
	place the arms in a position where the hand and forearm can
	truly rest, because it takes quite an effort to get in and out
	of these devices.  As a result, the strain on the forearms may
	be very significantly increased by using forearm rests.

	<h4>Contoured keyboards</h4> 

	In these keyboards, the majority of the keys are placed inside
	a depression along a curvature.  There is one depression for
	each hand, so that the keyboard may look like two bowls in a
	frame.  By matching the movement patterns on the fingers---the
	theory goes---these keyboard are easier on the body.  But
	precisely thanks to this property, the keyboard will force the
	hands into hovering in a specific position in space above it.
	In contrast, a flatter layout gives superior flexibility for
	striking the keys.
	
	<h4>Microswitch keyboards</h4> 
	<p>This paradigm stipulates again
	  that motion is at the heart of injury.  The keyboards
	  accommodate each finger in an individual fixed area or well in
	  close proximity to tiny switches.  Then minuscule movements of
	  fingers active switches.  Phenomenal typing speeds are
	  achievable.  I got the feeling when using a design of my own
	  of getting a kind of direct feed from brain to computer.  But
	  again, there is a fundamental misunderstanding at play if the
	  aim is to reduce physical strain: the body must continuously
	  adjust the position of all fingers so that they don't touch
	  the switches.  This compensation includes maintaining
	  positions of hands, forearms, not to say the whole body.
	  Again, the conventional keyboard is superior.  With it, the
	  hands are free all the time, except for the moment of strike,
	  to rest or to hover over the keyboard.
	</p>

	<h4>Tablets</h4> <p>It has been suggested that using a pen on
	  a tablet is more ergonomic than using a mouse.  Unfortunately,
	  there is a condition called writer's cramp that has been known
	  for hundreds, if not thousands of years, and it is likely to
	  affect the tablet user as well.  Holding a pen puts static
	  load on the whole upper body, so that the pen is not dropped
	  and does not touch the tablet when not in use.
	</p>

	<h4>Touch pads</h4> <p>So what about not holding anything at
	  all?  The touch pad offers such a solution, but as most people
	  have experienced, this technology does not work to well
	  either.  The cramped space is anything but natural for tracing
	  the movement of the cursor by using the index finger.  Even if
	  the touch pad was big enough that the whole hand could rest on
	  it, it would still induce static stress: the hand must be
	  turned so that the index finger does not touch the surface,
	  whenever the cursor is not moved.
	</p>

	<h4>Trackballs</h4> <p>There are good things be said about
	  trackballs: the hand may rest next to the device while the
	  cursor is not being moved.  Moving the cursor can be done with
	  the thumb or side of the hand.  Unfortunately, most trackballs
	  that are on the market have large, easily depressed buttons
	  surrounding the ball.  This "ergonomic" look probably have the
	  opposite effect: the hand constantly must balance itself to
	  not touch the buttons whenever near the device.  So, such
	  trackballs may be as harmful as ordinary mice.
	</p>

	<h4>So, what helps?</h4> <p>I believe that no tinkering with
	  keyboard or mouse design will lead to products that are
	  radically less stressful on the body.  Marginal improvements,
	  perhaps along the lines I've suggested, may be possible.
	  Ergonomic manuals consistently state that there is one way
	  only to effectively address severe cases of overuse syndromes:
	  complete and total cessation of the physical activity that led
	  to the problem.  Sometimes this cessation must be permanent,
	  often implying a loss of ability to work.  Finger and hand
	  work must be avoided in any form that resembles the
	  injury-causing way of working.</p>
	
	<p>An approach to reduce physical impact might be: type
	  with only the strongest fingers (thumb and index) and move a
	  mouse by pushing it with two hands resting on the
	  desk or keyboard tray.  Such behavioral techniques may offer
	  far greater 	 potential for reducing injury than any
	  changes 	 in device 	 design.  	 But their use
	  may 	 also lead 	 to 	 further
	  injury, given that 	 they represent a very different
	  approach than that of 	 complete 	 rest.  For lesser
	  injuries, 	 other 	 techniques are 	 possible as
	  is discussed in 	 books 	 on 	 computer-induced
	  injuries.
	</p>
	<p>In conclusion, I believe that avoidance and technique are
	  more important than device design.  Avoidance can be achieved
	  by a combination of speech recognition and foot pedals.  I
	  doubt that there are any other ways that are comparable in
	  efficiency.
	</p>
      </tab>
      <tab name="My Own Setup">
	<p>Here are some information about how I put my work
	  environment together.  For a picture of my workspace, see <a
	  href="../index_uisummary.html">User interface summary</a>.
	</p>

	<h3>Foot pedals</h3> 

	<p>It is difficult, if not impossible, to buy appropriate foot
	keyboards.  Foot switches that just float around on the floor
	are a bad idea.  Your feet won't be able to find them---and
	using them frequently may induce cramps in calf muscles.  Foot
	switches should be mounted on a foot rest.  A Y-key dual
	keyboard adaptor (from <a
	href="http://www.ymouse.com/">http://www.ymouse.com</a>)
	allows two keyboards to be used together.  Also, I believe
	that USB keyboards can be used in parallel.  In any case,
	individual foot switches can connected to the soldering points
	under each key on a second keyboard.  It's easiest to work
	with a keyboard equipped with mechanical switches, since
	capacitive switches may require the addition of a capacitor
	for each key.  The construction of a keyboard like the one
	shown probably can be done in a couple of days by somebody
	with electronic and woodworking skills.</p>

	<h3>Buttonless mice</h3>  
	<p>
	  Under Windows 2000 and XP, it is easy to make several mice
	  work together.  Personally, my favorite "ergonomic" mouse is
	  a 10 dollar device from Sakar International (Model #77452,
	  Iconcepts).  It is small so that the hand does not have to
	  struggle mounting it, and it is not too rounded.  I have
	  disabled the mouse buttons by sliding two thin slices of
	  rubber in the gap between the button and the case.  A better
	  alternative is to reshape an optical mouse, by peeling off
	  the upper casing; a better surface for grasping the mouse
	  can then be built out of epoxy or modeling clay.
	  Electrically, an ordinary foot switch or an extra key
	  mounted on the keyboard over a micro switch may be used to
	  short-circuit the two contact points of the micro switch
	  serving a button inside the mouse.  Thus, with relatively
	  modest soldering skills, one can connect a mouse
	  button switch via a second mouse (that is used solely for
	  this purpose).  Under Windows 2000 and XP, it is possible to
	  press the button of one mouse, while moving the other mouse,
	  to achieve the effect of dragging.  This is not possible
	  under some other operating systems, including Windows 98 and
	  Me.
	</p>
	<p>There might be easier ways to obtain a buttonless
	mouse---I have not investigated alternatives.
	</p>

	<h3>Wireless microphone</h3> <p>I like the design of the wired
	Emkay D-loop microphone.  It is very comfortable to wear, and
	the microphone stays in place.  Unfortunately, I have not been
	too impressed with the wireless consumer solutions that I've
	tested.  They do not provide a clean signal. Instead, I use a
	Shure LX wireless system.  The microphones that Shure provides
	come with elastic bands that wrap around your neck.  This a
	great solution for aerobics instructors---but an unworkable
	solution for speech recognition: you can't move your head
	without the microphone moving in front of your mouth.
	Instead, I have connected an Emkay D-loop microphone to the
	mini-XLR connector.  The details are: connect shield to pin 1
	and short-circuit pin 3 and pin 2 (which carries 5 V) and
	connect the hot wire (red) or pair of hot wires (red and
	white) to that short (inspiration for this operation is the
	diagram found at <a
	href="http://www.shure.com/pdf/userguides/guides_wiredmics/wcm16.pdf">http://www.shure.com/pdf/userguides/guides_wiredmics/wcm16.pdf</a>).
	To accomplish this wiring, I had to open the female mini-XLR
	connector.  To my knowledge, there is no mini-XLR to mini
	phone plug connector on the market.  I hope Bluetooth
	technology will be able to replace my LX system.
	</p>

	<h3>Keyboard</h3> 
	<p>I used to use an IBM keyboard without
	numeric keypad to gain space.  This excellent keyboard has
	mechanical switches and widely spaced Shft, Ctrl and Alt keys
	(IBM part no 1397681).  It is not made anymore.  My current
	keyboard is different, but since finally I am able to largely
	not use it, its design is not important.
	</p> 

	<h3>Computer </h3> <p>In my experience, Pentium III processors
	under 1 GHz are inadequate for speech recognition based on the
	NaturallySpeaking dictation system, now produced by Scansoft.
	The last year I have been using a AMD-based processor (Athlon
	1.4 GHz) with extremely nice results: response time for short
	utterances is very quick and the system altogether has been
	very stable. Half a Gb of RAM is required and sufficient.
	</p>
      </tab>
    </tabs>
  </body>
</html>

